<feed xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
      <title>Lagom Blog</title>
      <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog"/>
      <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/atom.xml"/>
      <id>https://www.lagomframework.com/blog</id>
      <rights>Copyright 2018, Lightbend</rights>
      <updated>2018-05-16T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
      <dc:creator>Lightbend</dc:creator>
      <dc:date>2018-05-16T00:00:00.000Z</dc:date>
      <dc:language>en</dc:language>
      <dc:rights>Copyright 2018, Lightbend</dc:rights>
      <entry>
          <title>Lagom 1.4.5 released!</title>
          <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/lagom-1.4.5.html"/>
          <category term="news" scheme="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/tags/news.html"/>
          <author>
            <name>Tim Moore</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/TimMoore</uri>
          </author>
          <id>https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/lagom-1.4.5.html</id>
          <updated>2018-05-16T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
          <published>2018-05-16T00:00:00.000Z</published>
          <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Lagom team has released Lagom 1.4.5.</p>
<p>This release provides several bug fixes and updates.</p>
<h2>Highlights:</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Updates Play to <a href="https://blog.playframework.com/play-2-6-13-released-2/">2.6.13</a></li>
  <li>Updates Akka to <a href="https://akka.io/blog/news/2018/04/13/akka-2.5.12-released">2.5.12</a></li>
  <li>Updates Akka HTTP to <a href="https://akka.io/blog/news/2018/03/23/akka-http-10.0.13-released">10.0.13</a></li>
  <li>Fixes a bug in the TestKit for services using RDBMS persistence that overrides the database driver selected in <code>application.conf</code> with H2 (<a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/pull/1297">#1297</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixes a bug in the RDBMS persistence module that could cause perpetual timeout errors if creating the offset table fails on startup (<a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/issues/1336">#1336</a>)</li>
</ul>
<p>See GitHub for the <a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/compare/1.4.4...1.4.5">full list of commits</a> and the issues and pull requests assigned to the <a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/milestone/30?closed=1">1.4.5 milestone</a>.</p>
<h2>Updating a Lagom project to version 1.4.5</h2>
<p>To update an sbt project, change the version of <code>lagom-sbt-plugin</code> in your <code>project/plugins.sbt</code> file.</p>
<p>To update a Maven project, change the <code>lagom.version</code> property in your top-level <code>pom.xml</code>.</p>
<p>After updating, it is recommended to fix any new deprecation warnings you see when compiling or running your services.</p>
<h2>Updating to sbt 1.x</h2>
<p>Support for sbt 1.x was quietly released with Lagom 1.4.0, but at the time we had not yet thoroughly tested it with Lagom, so we did not yet document this support or recommend it for most users.</p>
<p>Some adventurous users have been using it since then, and in the meantime we have updated all of our example applications and new project templates. Since we haven&rsquo;t encountered any new problems with sbt 1.x, we now recommend it for all users of Lagom with sbt.</p>
<p>You can update the sbt version in the <code>project/build.properties</code> file. The most recent version at the time of this writing is <a href="https://developer.lightbend.com/blog/2018-05-09-sbt-1-1-5-patch-release/">1.1.5</a>.</p>
<p>You might also need to update other plugins, global configuration, or custom build configuration. See the <a href="https://www.scala-sbt.org/1.x/docs/Migrating-from-sbt-013x.html">sbt documentation</a> for details on migrating from version 0.13.x.</p>
<h2><a href="#credits" name="credits">Credits</a></h2>
<p>Thanks to the community for their detailed bug reports and contributions.</p>
<p>Thanks to <a href="https://www.lightbend.com">Lightbend</a> for their continued sponsorship of the Lagom core team&rsquo;s efforts. Lightbend offers <a href="https://www.lightbend.com/subscription">commercial support</a> for Lagom.</p>
<p>Special thanks to the following contributors who helped with this release:</p>
<pre>
    8     342      81 Ignasi Marimon-Clos
    4     150      58 Tim Moore
    4       4       4 Play Team
    3       6       6 Brent Eritou
    2      57      40 Sebastien Coquelin
    1       1       3 Renato  Cavalcanti
    1      15      20 Jules Ivanic
    1       1       1 Riccardo Sirigu
    1      91      88 Patrick Prémont
    1      55       1 Kyle Florence
    1       8       6 Ido Shamun
    1      22       3 James Roper
</pre>]]></content>
          <dc:date>2018-05-16T00:00:00.000Z</dc:date>
        </entry><entry>
          <title>Lagom 1.4.4 released!</title>
          <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/lagom-1.4.4.html"/>
          <category term="news" scheme="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/tags/news.html"/>
          <author>
            <name>Renato Cavalcanti</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/renatocaval</uri>
          </author>
          <id>https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/lagom-1.4.4.html</id>
          <updated>2018-03-28T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
          <published>2018-03-28T00:00:00.000Z</published>
          <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Lagom team has released Lagom 1.4.4.<br/>(we are skipping 1.4.3 due to a small mistake in the release process)</p>
<p>This release provides a fix for <a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/issues/1250">#1250</a>. </p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/issues/1250">#1250</a> only affects Lagom projects making usage of JDBC persistence layer, being it for the journal and/or for read-side tables. </p>
<p>This release upgrades the versions of the underlying Slick library to <code>3.2.3</code> and the <code>akka-persistence-jdbc</code> plugin to version <code>3.3.0</code>.</p>
<h2>Slick 3.2.3 special note</h2>
<p>Since Slick 3.2.2, the <code>maxConnections</code> must equal <code>numThreads</code>. This is to prevent some situations where a deadlock could occur. A warning will be emitted in case <code>maxConnections &gt; numThreads</code> and a runtime exception will be thrown if <code>maxConnections &lt; numThreads</code>. Therefore the best possible configuration is <code>maxConnections == numThreads</code>. See <a href="https://github.com/slick/slick/pull/1855">slick/slick#1855</a> for detailed information.</p>
<p>These values are configured by Lagom automatically under the configuration key <code>db.default.async-executor</code>.</p>
<pre class="prettyprint"><code>db.default {
  async-executor {
    # number of objects that can be queued by the async executor
    queueSize = 10000
    
    # 5 * number of cores
    numThreads = 20

    # same as number number of threads
    minConnections = 20

    # same as number of threads
    maxConnections = 20
  }
}
</code></pre>
<p>If you haven&rsquo;t changed the settings for your <code>async-executor</code>, you have nothing to do. However, if you have configured your <code>aync-executor</code> with other values, you should review it and make sure that <code>maxThreads == maxConnections</code>.</p>
<p>See GitHub for the <a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/compare/1.4.2...1.4.4">full list of commits</a> and the issues and pull requests assigned to the <a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/milestone/29?closed=1">1.4.4 milestone</a>.</p>
<h2>Updating a Lagom project to version 1.4.4</h2>
<p>To update an sbt project, change the version of <code>lagom-sbt-plugin</code> in your <code>project/plugins.sbt</code> file.</p>
<p>To update a Maven project, change the <code>lagom.version</code> property in your top-level <code>pom.xml</code>.</p>
<p>After updating, it is recommended to fix any new deprecation warnings you see when compiling or running your services.</p>
<h2><a href="#credits" name="credits">Credits</a></h2>
<p>Thanks to the community for their detailed bug reports and contributions.</p>
<p>Thanks to <a href="https://www.lightbend.com">Lightbend</a> for their continued sponsorship of the Lagom core team&rsquo;s efforts. Lightbend offers <a href="https://www.lightbend.com/subscription">commercial support</a> for Lagom.</p>]]></content>
          <dc:date>2018-03-28T00:00:00.000Z</dc:date>
        </entry><entry>
          <title>Lagom 1.4.2/1.3.11 released!</title>
          <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/lagom-1-4-2-and-1-3-11.html"/>
          <category term="news" scheme="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/tags/news.html"/>
          <author>
            <name>Ignasi Marimon-Clos</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/ignasi35</uri>
          </author>
          <id>https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/lagom-1-4-2-and-1-3-11.html</id>
          <updated>2018-03-22T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
          <published>2018-03-22T00:00:00.000Z</published>
          <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Lagom team has released the versions 1.4.2 and 1.3.11. For a list of the specific changes in Lagom 1.4.2, see the <a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/changelog.html">change log</a>, and for a list of changes on Lagom 1.3.11 see the <a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/changelog-1.3.x.html">change log (1.3.x)</a>.</p>
<h2>Lagom 1.3.11</h2>
<p>This release provides several bug fixes and improvements. As an overview, this release contains the following:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Fixes a bug in loading settings from the <code>LagomClientFactory</code>. Special thanks to <a href="https://github.com/two10">two10</a> for the detailed report and bugfix suggestion. (<a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/pull/1256">#1256</a>)</li>
  <li>Adds out-of-the-box support for UUID&rsquo;s on the Path Params on your <code>Service.Descriptors</code>. (<a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/issues/1252">#1252</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixes Exception deserialization for <code>BadRequest</code>. (<a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/issues/1247">#1247</a>)</li>
  <li>Update to Scala 2.11.12. (<a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/issues/1197">#1197</a>)</li>
  <li>Added a check to warn about slow startup problems (thanks <a href="https://github.com/edmondo1984">Edmondo Porcu</a>). (<a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/issues/1112">#1112</a>)</li>
  <li>Improves error messages in path param serializer resolution (thanks <a href="https://github.com/silver-soule">Neelaksh</a>). (<a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/issues/1093">#1093</a>)</li>
  <li>Implementation review to allow mixed persistence using non-JDBC write-side with JDBC read-side (only applies to scala API). (<a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/pull/1100">#1100</a>)</li>
  <li>And several small improvements in the documentation!</li>
</ul>
<p>This release is the last including backports of general bugfixes and the <code>1.3.x</code> family may only get critical bugfixes backported onwards. If you are still using Lagom 1.3.x, we recommend you upgraded to latest versions of Lagom.</p>
<p>See GitHub for the <a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/compare/1.3.10...1.3.11">full list of commits</a> and the issues and pull requests assigned to the <a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/milestone/24?closed=1">1.3.11 milestone</a>.</p>
<h2>Lagom 1.4.2</h2>
<p>This release provides a few bug fixes and minor improvements over what 1.3.11 provides already (see the summary above). As an overview, this release contains the following:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Adds the message timestamp on the Kafka Message when using <a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/documentation/1.4.x/scala/MessageBrokerApi.html#Consuming-message-metadata">metadata-rich subscriptions</a>. (<a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/issues/1277">#1277</a>)</li>
  <li>Fixes a bug preventing conflicts between persistence backends when writing tests with mixed persistence (applies only to java API). ( <a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/issues/1263">#1263</a>)</li>
  <li>Added a timeout on the offset polling when starting a read-side to prevent a potential read-side block in certain failure scenarios. <a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/issues/1278">#1278</a></li>
</ul>
<p>See GitHub for the <a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/compare/1.4.1...1.4.2">full list of commits</a> and the issues and pull requests assigned to the <a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/milestone/28?closed=1">1.4.2 milestone</a>.</p>
<h2><a href="#credits" name="credits">Credits</a></h2>
<p>Thanks to the community for their detailed bug reports and contributions.</p>
<p>Thanks to <a href="https://www.lightbend.com">Lightbend</a> for their continued sponsorship of the Lagom core team&rsquo;s efforts. Lightbend offers <a href="https://www.lightbend.com/subscription">commercial support</a> for Lagom.</p>
<p>Special thanks to the following contributors who helped with the release 1.3.11:</p>
<pre class="prettyprint"><code>commits  added  removed
    9     117      68 Tim Moore
    6     254      35 Ignasi Marimon-Clos
    6     668     605 Renato Cavalcanti
    2       6       6 Sarun Rattanasiri
    1       1       1 Bruno Unna
    1      11      76 Ruth Stento
    1      31       7 Lutz Huehnken
    1      19       0 Edmondo Porcu
    1      59       5 Neelaksh
    1       1       1 Brent Eritou
</code></pre>
<p>Special thanks to the following contributors who helped with the release 1.4.2:</p>
<pre class="prettyprint"><code>commits  added  removed
      9     291      56 Ignasi Marimon-Clos
      6     176     139 Tim Moore
      1      23       5 Renato Cavalcanti
      1      12       0 Jason Pickens
</code></pre>]]></content>
          <dc:date>2018-03-22T00:00:00.000Z</dc:date>
        </entry><entry>
          <title>From CRUD to Event Sourcing</title>
          <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/event-sourcing-vs-crud.html"/>
          <category term="event sourcing" scheme="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/tags/event%20sourcing.html"/><category term="crud" scheme="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/tags/crud.html"/>
          <author>
            <name>James Roper</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/jroper</uri>
          </author>
          <id>https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/event-sourcing-vs-crud.html</id>
          <updated>2018-03-20T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
          <published>2018-03-20T00:00:00.000Z</published>
          <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As the Lagom project has grown in usage, one of the biggest barriers to adoption that we&rsquo;ve seen is Lagom&rsquo;s opinionated approach to using event sourcing for persistence. Many developers looking to write reactive microservices come from a <a href="https://www.codecademy.com/articles/what-is-crud">CRUD</a> background, often using relational databases to store data.</p>
<p>Lagom&rsquo;s service API can be used alongside CRUD-style persistence - you can easily use any persistence technology available on the JVM in Lagom. However, the Lagom persistence APIs do not offer CRUD as a first class option, and the <a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/documentation/1.4.x/java/PersistentEntity.html">Lagom documentation</a> pushes users in the direction of event sourcing.</p>
<p>To be honest, event sourcing does generally require writing more code up front than CRUD. Lagom does not push event sourcing because it reduces the amount of code. Lagom pushes event sourcing because the problems that microservices introduce - such as ensuring consistency between services - are very easily solved when you are using event sourcing for persistence, and very hard to solve when you&rsquo;re using CRUD for persistence. A service using CRUD might have less code to start with, but as soon as it starts sharing data with other services, problems relating to handling failures and synchronisation of state become very difficult problems to solve, and will often require implementing complex solutions, including manual state and failure tracking. In fact, in my experience of using CRUD, dealing with these problems usually requires manually implementing event logs and asynchronous batch processes to handle them, so developers end up implementing both event sourcing and CRUD, which is far more code and far harder to maintain. In contrast, event sourcing inherently deals with these problems as a property of the architectural approach, with no special code implemented by developers.</p>
<p>Put simply, using event sourcing over CRUD is an investment of more code and effort up front, but will yield a simpler, more resilient and easier to maintain system in the future. Lets take a look at how this looks in practice.</p>
<p>A few months ago I had the chance to speak about this topic at the Reactive Summit&rsquo;17. Here&rsquo;s the recording of the talk.</p>
<div id="meet-lagom" class="flex-video widescreen">
  <iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/holjbuSbv3k" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen="" mozallowfullscreen="" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>]]></content>
          <dc:date>2018-03-20T00:00:00.000Z</dc:date>
        </entry><entry>
          <title>Introducing discuss.lagomframework.com</title>
          <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/announcing-discuss-lagomframework-forum.html"/>
          <category term="news" scheme="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/tags/news.html"/><category term="discuss" scheme="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/tags/discuss.html"/>
          <author>
            <name>Tim Moore</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/TimMoore</uri>
          </author>
          <id>https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/announcing-discuss-lagomframework-forum.html</id>
          <updated>2018-03-13T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
          <published>2018-03-13T00:00:00.000Z</published>
          <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We are pleased to announce a new way to communicate with the Lagom community: <a href="https://discuss.lagomframework.com">discuss.lagomframework.com</a>.</p>
<p>It is a <a href="https://www.discourse.org/">Discourse</a> forum sponsored by <a href="https://www.lightbend.com/">Lightbend</a>, and co-hosted under the discuss.lightbend.com domain, along with discuss.playframework.com and discuss.akka.io. Each of these domains redirects you to the main category for the corresponding project, so you can go directly to the Lagom discussions by using the discuss.lagomframework.com shortcut, without having to navigate through the entire list of all categories. At the same time, discussions relating to the foundational technologies that Lagom is built on are right within reach on the same site. This will make it simpler for the Akka, Play, and Lagom communities to learn from each other and share ideas.</p>
<p>To further explain what&rsquo;s going to happen next to the other communication channels, and what their intended use is:</p>
<h2>What happens to the lagom-framework mailing list?</h2>
<p>The lagom-framework mailing list on Google Groups will be transitioned into a read-only mode. It will not happen immediately, but we&rsquo;ll try to direct all new questions to the new forum, and eventually flip the switch to mark lagom-framework as a read-only archive.</p>
<p>We took this decision after much thought, debate and considering the various up and down sides of handling it very seriously. We know that a mailing list work-flow is very precious for people used to working with them (plenty of us including), however in order to grow the community as a whole, and also help making the discussions on such forum more searchable and accessible, we decided that this move will be beneficial for everyone involved.</p>
<p>If you enjoy working with mailing lists, and would like to continue to do so with the new forums, please have a look at the <a href="https://discuss.lightbend.com/c/meta">hints in the Discuss Meta topics</a>, where we prepared hints on how to set up the <a href="https://discuss.lightbend.com/t/how-to-use-the-discuss-forum-as-a-mailing-list/61">notifications to work as-if a mailing list</a>.</p>
<h2><a href="#what-happens-to-the-gitter-channels-" name="what-happens-to-the-gitter-channels-">What happens to the Gitter channels?</a></h2>
<p>The <a href="https://gitter.im/lagom/lagom">Lagom Gitter room</a> and <a href="https://gitter.im/lagom/contributors">Lagom contributors Gitter room</a> will remain as real-time chat channels, but we suggest posting questions in discuss.lagomframework.com if you don&rsquo;t get a quick response. With the Lagom community and maintainer team distributed around the world, not everyone can take part in a conversation on Gitter at the same time. With Gitter&rsquo;s linear and conversational format, it can be hard to keep track of concurrent discussions, and it&rsquo;s easy to miss messages. The new forum will make it much easier to keep track of the conversations you are interested in, and ignore the ones you aren&rsquo;t. Asynchronous communication is not just for microservices!</p>
<h2><a href="#what-other-community-channels-are-there-" name="what-other-community-channels-are-there-">What other community channels are there?</a></h2>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/tagged/lagom">Stack Overflow</a> is still a great place to ask specific programming questions about Lagom, especially when they also relate to other technologies that are not part of discuss.lightbend.com. Stack Overflow has a huge community, and the Lagom maintainer team continues to monitor the &ldquo;lagom&rdquo; tag on it. However, Stack Overflow has a strict Q&amp;A format and <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/help/on-topic">rules about what is considered on-topic</a>. It is not suitable for opinion-based questions, announcements, or open-ended discussion.</li>
  <li>Of course, <a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom">GitHub</a> is the center for collaboration on development of Lagom itself, and the <a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/issues">issue tracker</a> is the best place to report reproducible bugs and propose new features. If you&rsquo;re having a problem and you&rsquo;re not sure if it&rsquo;s caused by a bug in Lagom, please ask for help on discuss.lagomframework.com before creating an issue on GitHub.</li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="#what-if-i-want-urgent-24-7-support-" name="what-if-i-want-urgent-24-7-support-">What if I want urgent 24/7 support?</a></h2>
<p>Nothing changes in this aspect. The public communication channels were always best-effort, although we and the community do try to help as much as possible. If you really want the best-in-class, most responsive answers and support, the <a href="https://www.lightbend.com/subscription">Lightbend Subscription</a> offers professional development and production support, along with access to consulting services, training, the <a href="https://www.lightbend.com/products/enterprise-suite">Lightbend Enterprise Suite</a> of commercial software, and other benefits.</p>
<p>It is important to highlight that the move to the &ldquo;discuss&rdquo; forum (as we like to call it) is not the same as commercial support, however we do hope to serve our communities better by making this move. We do not envision any negative impact on the quality of the answers you have been receiving on Gitter and lagom-framework by this move to the new forums.</p>
<p>We hope you&rsquo;re as excited about the new discussion forums as we are. We look forward to you joining us there!</p>]]></content>
          <dc:date>2018-03-13T00:00:00.000Z</dc:date>
        </entry><entry>
          <title>Lagom 1.4.1 released!</title>
          <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/lagom-1-4-1.html"/>
          <category term="news" scheme="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/tags/news.html"/>
          <author>
            <name>Tim Moore</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/TimMoore</uri>
          </author>
          <id>https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/lagom-1-4-1.html</id>
          <updated>2018-03-06T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
          <published>2018-03-06T00:00:00.000Z</published>
          <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Lagom team has released Lagom 1.4.1. For a list of the specific changes in Lagom 1.4.1, see the <a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/changelog.html">change log</a>.</p>
<p>This release provides a few bug fixes and minor improvements. As an overview, this release contains the following:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Updates Akka Persistence Cassandra to 0.60, which updates the bundled Cassandra version to 3.11.2. This fixes a crash on startup when using JDK versions 1.8.0_161 and later. (<a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/issues/1204">#1204</a>)</li>
  <li>Updates Akka to <a href="https://akka.io/blog/news/2018/02/28/akka-2.5.11-released">2.5.11</a> (also includes changes from <a href="https://akka.io/blog/news/2018/02/23/akka-2.5.10-released">2.5.10</a>).</li>
  <li>Updates Play to <a href="https://blog.playframework.com/play-2-6-12-released/">2.6.12</a>.</li>
  <li>Prevents <code>SaveSnapshotSuccess</code> from showing up in unhandled messages. (<a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/issues/1209">#1209</a>)</li>
</ul>
<p>See GitHub for the <a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/compare/1.4.0...1.4.1">full list of commits</a> and the issues and pull requests assigned to the <a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/milestone/27?closed=1">1.4.1 milestone</a>.</p>
<h2>Updating a Lagom project to version 1.4.1</h2>
<p>To update an sbt project, change the version of <code>lagom-sbt-plugin</code> in your <code>project/plugins.sbt</code> file.</p>
<p>To update a Maven project, change the <code>lagom.version</code> property in your top-level <code>pom.xml</code>.</p>
<p>After updating, it is recommended to fix any new deprecation warnings you see when compiling or running your services.</p>
<h2><a href="#credits" name="credits">Credits</a></h2>
<p>Thanks to the community for their detailed bug reports and contributions.</p>
<p>Thanks to <a href="https://www.lightbend.com">Lightbend</a> for their continued sponsorship of the Lagom core team&rsquo;s efforts. Lightbend offers <a href="https://www.lightbend.com/subscription">commercial support</a> for Lagom.</p>
<p>Special thanks to the following contributors who helped with this release:</p>
<pre class="prettyprint"><code>commits  added  removed
      6     87       60  Tim Moore
      3     54      123  Renato Cavalcanti
      1     31        7  Lutz Huehnken
</code></pre>]]></content>
          <dc:date>2018-03-06T00:00:00.000Z</dc:date>
        </entry><entry>
          <title>Introducing the Lagom Recipes</title>
          <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/announcing-lagom-recipes.html"/>
          <category term="news" scheme="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/tags/news.html"/><category term="recipes" scheme="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/tags/recipes.html"/><category term="cookbook" scheme="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/tags/cookbook.html"/>
          <author>
            <name>Ignasi Marimon-Clos</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/ignasi35</uri>
          </author>
          <id>https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/announcing-lagom-recipes.html</id>
          <updated>2018-02-13T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
          <published>2018-02-13T00:00:00.000Z</published>
          <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Lagom is an OSS framework to build microservice-based software systems. At Lightbend we sponsor the development of the framework and encourage contributions from the community, but we also help people get started, be more productive when using it or solve the bugs there may be in the framework code. We participate on the <a href="https://discuss.lagomframework.com">Discuss Lagom Forum</a>, <a href="https://gitter.im/lagom/lagom">Gitter</a> channel and, of course, <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/tagged/lagom">Stack Overflow</a> and <a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/issues">GitHub issues</a>, but Lightbend also provides support for its <a href="https://www.lightbend.com/subscription">subscribers</a> using Lagom. We sometimes detect the same questions pop up repeatedly on those channels of support. In order to reduce repeating the same answers over and over and because common problems should have readily available solutions, we created the <a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom-recipes">Lagom Recipes</a> repository.</p>
<h3><a href="#lagom-recipes" name="lagom-recipes">Lagom Recipes</a></h3>
<p>Like a cookbook, the Lagom recipes repository contains a varied list of step-by-step solutions to common problems Lagom developers may face. Take for example the common request on the Mailing List: &ldquo;How do I enable CORS for my Lagom API?&rdquo;. It&rsquo;s a simple enough request but in Lagom the solution is slightly different whether you are using the <code>javadsl</code> or the <code>scaladsl</code> so the common response to such a question was &ldquo;Are you using java or scala?&rdquo;. It&rsquo;s a problem which involves some knowledge of <a href="https://www.playframework.com/">Play</a> which is a building block of Lagom. Therefore the explanation ends up being a bit confusing. It is easier to prepare two recipes to answer the question for Java or Scala developers in mind and explain each step on the README.</p>
<p>Every recipe may contain a README file detailing the what files would you need to add or edit in order to complete the recipe. On top of that, recipes are not meant to start a project from scratch. Instead, each recipe details the necessary increment over an existing Lagom Service or a complete Lagom system of many services. The recipe is usually developed in few separate commits to demonstrate the increment necessary to complete your goal:</p>
<ul>
  <li>a first commit sets up the minimum Lagom system</li>
  <li>a second commit introduces the changes necessary to complete the task and the README file explaining the changes.</li>
</ul>
<p>The current list of recipes includes solutions for problems such as:</p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom-recipes/tree/master/cors">How do I enable CORS</a>?</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom-recipes/tree/master/consumer-service">How do I create a Subscriber only service</a>?</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom-recipes/tree/master/mixed-persistence">How do I use RDBMS read-sides with Cassandra write-sides</a>?</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom-recipes/tree/master/i18n">How do I create a stateless service in Lagom for Java that uses Play&rsquo;s Internationalization Support</a>?</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom-recipes/tree/master/http-header-handling">How do I manipulate Headers and Status Codes and test those cases</a>?</li>
</ul>
<p>We hope adding this learning resource to the list of <a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/documentation/">documentation resources</a> already available will help create great applications!</p>]]></content>
          <dc:date>2018-02-13T00:00:00.000Z</dc:date>
        </entry><entry>
          <title>Lagom 1.4.0 released!</title>
          <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/lagom-1-4-0.html"/>
          <category term="news" scheme="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/tags/news.html"/>
          <author>
            <name>Tim Moore</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/TimMoore</uri>
          </author>
          <id>https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/lagom-1-4-0.html</id>
          <updated>2018-01-25T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
          <published>2018-01-25T00:00:00.000Z</published>
          <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We are pleased to announce the immediate availability of Lagom 1.4.0!</p>
<p>Lagom 1.4 brings many internal updates, small features, and other improvements:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Akka, Play, Slick and many other components included with Lagom have been updated to the latest versions, bringing along many new features and improvements.</li>
  <li>The Lagom TestKit now supports testing services that use RDBMS persistence.</li>
  <li>Scala users can write read-side processors using Slick.</li>
  <li>Akka HTTP replaces Netty as the default server engine in Lagom (Netty is still supported).</li>
  <li>Scala 2.12 support, providing smaller, better optimized deployment artifacts even for Java users (2.11 is still supported).</li>
  <li>A new and growing set of <a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom-recipes">&ldquo;Lagom Recipes&rdquo;</a> providing code examples for common use-cases.</li>
  <li>&hellip;and many more smaller changes. A list of all changes since 1.3 or 1.4.0-RC1 can be found in the <a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/changelog.html">Change Log</a>.</li>
</ul>
<h2>What to do next:</h2>
<ul>
  <li>To start a Lagom 1.4 project right away, visit the <a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/get-started.html">Try Lagom</a> page.</li>
  <li>If you are currently using an earlier version of Lagom, check the migration guide for <a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/documentation/1.4.x/java/Migration14.html">Java</a> or <a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/documentation/1.4.x/scala/Migration14.html">Scala</a>.</li>
</ul>
<h2><a href="#credits" name="credits">Credits</a></h2>
<p>Thanks to the community for their detailed bug reports and contributions.</p>
<p>Thanks to <a href="https://www.lightbend.com">Lightbend</a> for their continued sponsorship of the Lagom core team&rsquo;s efforts. Lightbend offers <a href="https://www.lightbend.com/subscription">commercial support</a> for Lagom.</p>
<p>Special thanks to the following contributors who helped with this release:</p>
<pre class="prettyprint"><code>commits  added  removed
     63   3918     2650  Ignasi Marimon-Clos
     60   1995     1590  Tim Moore
     41   4381     2819  Renato Cavalcanti
     21   3008     1096  James Roper
      9   1040      655  Ruth Stento
      7    266      142  Elijah Rippeth
      5     31       53  Markus Jura
      5    296      153  Greg Methvin
      5     55      141  Yuliana Apaza
      4     54        5  Jules Ivanic
      3     53       52  Pallavi Singh
      3    531      499  Marcos Pereira
      3      5        5  Ben McCann
      2      2        2  mihbor
      2      2        2  t-h-a-l-i-s
      2      4        2  dr3s
      2      6        6  Sarun Rattanasiri
      2     67       29  Wayne Wang
      2     25        6  Carlos R. Feliz
      2     40       62  Himani Arora
      2     36       39  Jirka Kremser
      2     37        1  Micho
      2     84       12  Edouard Kaiser
      1      1        2  Dominik Kunz
      1     71        8  Adam Chaulk
      1      2        2  NOUGUIER Olivier
      1      3        1  Renato  Cavalcanti
      1     10        1  Yura Taras
      1     39        8  Neelaksh
      1    196       12  Matthias Kurz
      1      1        1  Stijn De Haes
      1     17        1  HSalaila
      1      5        6  Jaie Wilson
      1     75       16  datalchemist
      1      6        0  Saniya Tech
      1     24        6  Olivier Deckers
      1      3        3  Evander Otieno
      1      1        1  Jimin Hsieh
      1     19        0  Edmondo Porcu
      1    309       21  Julien Jean Paul Sirocchi
      1      1        1  Scott Langley
      1     77       12  Mick Jermsak Jermsurawong
      1      1        1  Harsh Sharma
      1     85       39  Vladimir Shin
      1    222       78  Pawel
      1      1        1  Toshiyuki Takahashi
      1      1        1  Brent Eritou
      1      1        1  Oliver Wickham
      1      4       36  Christopher Hunt
      1      2        2  surya prakash singh
      1     68        0  Miel Donkers
      1      1        1  Ashish Tomer
      1      1        1  Tim Sheils
      1      1        1  Shifeng Zhang
</code></pre>]]></content>
          <dc:date>2018-01-25T00:00:00.000Z</dc:date>
        </entry><entry>
          <title>Lagom 1.4.0-RC1</title>
          <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/lagom-1-4-0-RC1.html"/>
          <category term="news" scheme="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/tags/news.html"/>
          <author>
            <name>Renato Cavalcanti</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/renatocaval</uri>
          </author>
          <id>https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/lagom-1-4-0-RC1.html</id>
          <updated>2017-12-22T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
          <published>2017-12-22T00:00:00.000Z</published>
          <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s Christmas! And we are very pleased to announce the availability of the first release candidate of Lagom 1.4.0. What a nice present to spent your time during the holiday season! :-)</p>
<p>Contrary to the previous milestone releases, a RC is production ready. We are now entering the release candidate phase (typically 4 weeks) in which only major bugs (if any) will be fixed. </p>
<h3><a href="#migrating-from-other-versions" name="migrating-from-other-versions">Migrating from other versions</a></h3>
<ul>
  <li>If you are migrating to Lagom 1.4.0-RC1 from 1.4.0-M3, look out for new deprecation warnings. The migration guide to 1.4 (<a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/documentation/1.4.x/java/Migration14.html">Java</a>/<a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/documentation/1.4.x/scala/Migration14.html">Scala</a>) has also been improved, don&rsquo;t forget to review it.</li>
  <li>If you are migrating into Lagom 1.4.0-RC1 from a version in the Lagom 1.3.x series you should have a look at changes introduced in latest versions of the Lagom 1.3.x series and especially you should read the migration guide to 1.4 (<a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/documentation/1.4.x/java/Migration14.html">Java</a>/<a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/documentation/1.4.x/scala/Migration14.html">Scala</a>). We also recommend updating to the latest stable 1.3.x release (currently 1.3.10 as of this writing) before attempting to update to 1.4.</li>
</ul>
<h3><a href="#changelog" name="changelog">Changelog</a></h3>
<p>See the <a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/compare/1.4.0-M3...1.4.0-RC1">full list of changes</a> and the <a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/milestone/25?closed=1">1.4.0-RC1 milestone</a> on GitHub. The changes includes a few bug fixes and improvements, some of which we highlight below: </p>
<ul>
  <li>Ensure Akka cluster is left gracefully based on new <a href="https://doc.akka.io/docs/akka/current/actors.html?language=scala#coordinated-shutdown">Akka Coordinated Shutdown</a></li>
  <li>Maven Dependency POM and Archetype supporting Scala 2.11 and 2.12</li>
  <li>Upgraded to Akka 2.5.8</li>
  <li>Upgraded to Akka HTTP 10.0.11</li>
  <li>Upgraded to Play 2.6.10</li>
  <li>Upgraded to akka-persistence-jdbc to 3.1.0</li>
  <li>Akka HTTP as default backend</li>
  <li>maxFrameLength config parameter for WebSocketClient</li>
</ul>
<h3><a href="#credits" name="credits">Credits</a></h3>
<p>Thanks to the community for their detailed bug reports and contributions.</p>
<p>Thanks to <a href="https://www.lightbend.com">Lightbend</a> for their continued sponsorship of the Lagom core team&rsquo;s efforts. Lightbend offers <a href="https://www.lightbend.com/subscription">commercial support</a> for Lagom.</p>
<p>Special thanks to the following contributors who helped with this release: <em>Tim Moore, Renato Cavalcanti, Ignasi Marimon-Clos, James Roper, Edmondo Porcu and datalchemist</em>.<br/>```</p>]]></content>
          <dc:date>2017-12-22T00:00:00.000Z</dc:date>
        </entry><entry>
          <title>Lagom 1.4.0-M3</title>
          <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/lagom-1-4-0-M3.html"/>
          <category term="news" scheme="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/tags/news.html"/>
          <author>
            <name>Tim Moore</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/TimMoore</uri>
          </author>
          <id>https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/lagom-1-4-0-M3.html</id>
          <updated>2017-11-30T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
          <published>2017-11-30T00:00:00.000Z</published>
          <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We are very pleased to announce the availability of the third milestone release of Lagom 1.4.0. Although we had originally hoped to have a release candidate available by now, there are still a few <a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/milestone/25">known issues</a> with the 1.4.0 release that will take a little time to complete. In the meantime, there are enough changes since M2 that we decided to publish a new milestone to allow users on the bleeding edge to give them a try. Thanks for your patience!</p>
<p>Please note that we still do not recommend using a milestone release in production, as there may still be incompatible changes up until the first release candidate.</p>
<h3><a href="#migrating-from-other-versions" name="migrating-from-other-versions">Migrating from other versions</a></h3>
<ul>
  <li>If you are migrating into Lagom 1.4.0-M3 from 1.4.0-M2 you should have a look at the release announcements for Lagom versions <a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/lagom-1-3-9.html">1.3.9</a> and <a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/blog/lagom-1-3-10.html">1.3.10</a>. The migration guide to 1.4 (<a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/documentation/1.4.x/java/Migration14.html">Java</a>/<a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/documentation/1.4.x/scala/Migration14.html">Scala</a>) has also been improved, don&rsquo;t forget to review it.</li>
  <li>If you are migrating into Lagom 1.4.0-M3 from a version in the Lagom 1.3.x series you should have a look at changes introduced in latest versions of the Lagom 1.3.x series and especially you should read the migration guide to 1.4 (<a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/documentation/1.4.x/java/Migration14.html">Java</a>/<a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/documentation/1.4.x/scala/Migration14.html">Scala</a>). We also recommend updating to the latest stable 1.3.x release (currently 1.3.10 as of this writing) before attempting to update to 1.4.</li>
</ul>
<h3><a href="#improvements" name="improvements">Improvements</a></h3>
<ul>
  <li>The Lagom circuit breaker can be configured to ignore certain exceptions. These exceptions will still be seen by the client, but they will no longer cause the circuit breaker to open. See the documentation on circuit breaker configuration (<a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/documentation/1.4.x/java/ServiceClients.html#Circuit-Breaker-Configuration">Java</a>/<a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/documentation/1.4.x/scala/ServiceClients.html#Circuit-Breaker-Configuration">Scala</a>) and service error handling (<a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/documentation/1.4.x/java/ServiceErrorHandling.html">Java</a>/<a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/documentation/1.4.x/scala/ServiceErrorHandling.html">Scala</a>) for more details.</li>
  <li>You can now <a href="https://github.com/lagom/lagom/pull/1010">disable entity passivation</a> by setting <code>lagom.persistence.passivate-after-idle-timeout = 0</code> in <code>application.conf</code>. This allows your service to keep all entities resident in memory or control passivation more directly.</li>
  <li>The Message Broker API now provides the <code>Subscriber.withMetadata</code> method to allow consumers to access details about each method such as the Kafka message key. See the documentation on consuming message metadata (<a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/documentation/1.4.x/java/MessageBrokerApi.html#Consuming-message-metadata">Java</a>/<a href="https://www.lagomframework.com/documentation/1.4.x/scala/MessageBrokerApi.html#Consuming-message-metadata">Scala</a>) for details.</li>
  <li>The default port for the development mode service locator changed from 8000 to 9008. This is rarely used directly, so it should be transparent for most users, but 8000 is a common port for other services to run on (including the default debug port used by <code>mvnDebug</code>), so this will reduce the chance of conflicts.</li>
  <li>Several underlying dependencies were updated (including Play and Akka)</li>
</ul>
<h3><a href="#contributors" name="contributors">Contributors</a></h3>
<p>The Lagom maintainer team extends its gratitude to all of the people who have contributed to the release. There are now enough of you that we&rsquo;ve decided to borrow <a href="https://github.com/akka/akka/blob/master/scripts/authors.pl">Akka&rsquo;s credits script</a> to summarize the results:</p>
<pre class="prettyprint"><code>commits added removed
    7     324      42 Renato Cavalcanti
    7     884     249 Ignasi Marimon-Clos
    6     286     256 Tim Moore
    5     296     153 Greg Methvin
    4     803     128 James Roper
    3      53      52 Pallavi Singh
    2      55       7 Elijah Rippeth
    2      36      39 Jirka Kremser
    1       6       0 Saniya Tech
    1       6       5 Marcos Pereira
    1      17       1 HSalaila
    1      71       8 Adam Chaulk
    1     309      21 Julien Jean Paul Sirocchi
    1       2       2 NOUGUIER Olivier
    1      39       8 Neelaksh
    1      36       0 Micho
    1       3       1 dr3s
    1      11      76 Ruth Stento
    1       1       1 Stijn De Haes
</code></pre>]]></content>
          <dc:date>2017-11-30T00:00:00.000Z</dc:date>
        </entry>
    </feed>